When we think about prejudice and bias,
حين نفكر في التعصب والتحيز،
we tend to think about stupid and evil people
نميل إلى التفكير في أناس أغبياء وأشرار
doing stupid and evil things.
يقومون بأعمال غبية وشريرة.
And this idea is nicely summarized
ويلخص هذه الفكرة بشكل جيد
by the British critic William Hazlitt,
الناقد البريطاني ويليام هازليت،
who wrote, "Prejudice is the child of ignorance."
الذي كتب، "التعصب ابن الجهل."
I want to try to convince you here
أريد هنا محاولة إقناعكم
that this is mistaken.
أن هذا خطأ
I want to try to convince you
أريد محاولة إقناعكم
that prejudice and bias
أن التعصب والتحيز
are natural, they're often rational,
طبيعيان، وهما غالبًا عقلانيان،
and they're often even moral,
وهما في الغالب أخلاقيان حتى،
and I think that once we understand this,
وأعتقد أنه بمجرد أن نستوعب هذا،
we're in a better position to make sense of them
سنكون في وضع أفضل لنصحح لهم
when they go wrong,
حين يذهبون للطريق الخطأ
when they have horrible consequences,
حين يحصلون على عواقب رهيبة،
and we're in a better position to know what to do
ونكون في وضع أفضل لنعرف ما نفعل
when this happens.
حين يحدث هذا.
So, start with stereotypes. You look at me,
حسنًا، نبدأ بالصور النمطية، أنتم تنظورن إليَّ،
you know my name, you know certain facts about me,
تعرفون اسمي، تعرفون حقائق محددة عني،
and you could make certain judgments.
ويمكنكم إجراء أحكام محددة.
You could make guesses about my ethnicity,
يمكنكم تخمين إلى أي عرقٍ أنتمي،
my political affiliation, my religious beliefs.
إنتمائي السياسي، معتقداتي الدينية.
And the thing is, these judgments tend to be accurate.
والأمر هو، تميل هذه الأحكام للدقة.
We're very good at this sort of thing.
نحن جيدون جدًا في ذلك النوع من المسائل.
And we're very good at this sort of thing
ونحن جيدون جدًا في هذا النوع
because our ability to stereotype people
لأن قدرتنا على قولبة الناس
is not some sort of arbitrary quirk of the mind,
ليست نوعًا من هوس التعسف العقلي،
but rather it's a specific instance
بل إنها حالة معينة
of a more general process,
من أكثر من عملية عامة،
which is that we have experience
والتي هى أن لدينا خبرة
with things and people in the world
مع الأشياء والناس في العالم
that fall into categories,
التي تقع ضمن فئات،
and we can use our experience to make generalizations
ويمكننا استخدام خبرتنا للتعميم
about novel instances of these categories.
لحالات جديدة من هذه الفئات.
So everybody here has a lot of experience
إذًا كل فرد هنا لديه العديد من الخبرات
with chairs and apples and dogs,
مع الكراسي والتفاح والكلاب،
and based on this, you could see
واعتمادا على هذا، يمكنكم أن تروا
unfamiliar examples and you could guess,
أمثلة غير مألوفة ويمكنكم التخمين
you could sit on the chair,
يمكنكم الجلوس على كرسي،
you could eat the apple, the dog will bark.
يمكنكم أكل تفاحة، والكلب سوف ينبح.
Now we might be wrong.
الآن ربما نكون مخطئين.
The chair could collapse if you sit on it,
الكرسي يمكن أن يتحطم إن جلست عليه،
the apple might be poison, the dog might not bark,
التفاحة يمكن أن تكون فاسدة، الكلب قد لا ينبح،
and in fact, this is my dog Tessie, who doesn't bark.
وفي واقع الأمر، هذا كلبي تيسي، الذي لا ينبح.
But for the most part, we're good at this.
لكن معظم الأحيان، نحن جيدون في هذا.
For the most part, we make good guesses
في معظم الأحيان، نقوم بتخمينات جيدة
both in the social domain and the non-social domain,
في المجالين الإجتماعي والغير إجتماعي
and if we weren't able to do so,
وإن لم يكن لدينا القدرة على القيام بذلك،
if we weren't able to make guesses about new instances that we encounter,
إن لم يكن لدينا القدرة على تخمين الحالات الجديدة التي نقابلها،
we wouldn't survive.
لن نبقى على قيد الحياة.
And in fact, Hazlitt later on in his wonderful essay
وفي واقع الأمر، يعترف هازليت لاحقًا
concedes this.
في مقالته الرائعة بهذا.
He writes, "Without the aid of prejudice and custom,
كتب، "بدون مساعدة التعصب والعرف،
I should not be able to find my way my across the room;
لن تكون لي المقدرة لأجد طريقي في أنحاء الغرفة؛
nor know how to conduct myself in any circumstances,
ولا أعرف كيف أدبر نفسي في أي ظروف،
nor what to feel in any relation of life."
ولا ما أشعر في أي علاقة في الحياة."
Or take bias.
أو اتخاذ التحيز.
Now sometimes, we break the world up into
الآن في بعض الأحيان، نفرق العالم إلى
us versus them, into in-group versus out-group,
نحن، ضدهم، إلى داخل المجموعة في مقابل خارج المجموعة،
and sometimes when we do this,
وأحيانا حين نقوم بذلك،
we know we're doing something wrong,
نحن نعلم أننا نقوم بشيء خطأ،
and we're kind of ashamed of it.
ونخجل منه شيءً ما.
But other times we're proud of it.
لكن في أحيان أخرى نفتخر به.
We openly acknowledge it.
نعترف به علنًا
And my favorite example of this
ومثالي المفضل على هذا
is a question that came from the audience
هو سؤال جاء من مستمعة
in a Republican debate prior to the last election.
في مناظرة الجمهوريين قبل الانتخابات الأخيرة.
(Video) Anderson Cooper: Gets to your question,
(فيديو) أندرسون كوبر: حصلت على سؤالك،
the question in the hall, on foreign aid? Yes, ma'am.
سؤالك في القاعة، عن المساعدات الخارجية؟ نعم، سيدتي.
Woman: The American people are suffering
سيدة: الشعب الأمريكي يعاني
in our country right now.
في بلادنا حاليًا.
Why do we continue to send foreign aid
لماذا نستمر في إرسال مساعدات خارجية
to other countries
لبلدان أخرى
when we need all the help we can get for ourselves?
في حين نحتاج نحن كل المساعدة التي نستطيع أن نتحصل عليها لأنفسنا؟
AC: Governor Perry, what about that?
أندرسون: ماذا عن ذلك محافظ بيري؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Rick Perry: Absolutely, I think it's—
ريك بيري: إطلاقًا، أعتقد أن هذا -
Paul Bloom: Each of the people onstage
بول بلوم: كل الناس على المسرح
agreed with the premise of her question,
وافقوا على فرضية سؤالها،
which is as Americans, we should care more
الذي هو كأمريكيين، يجب أن نعتني
about Americans than about other people.
بالأمريكيين أكثر من الناس الآخرين.
And in fact, in general, people are often swayed
والأمر الواقع، في العموم، الناس في الغالب يُحكمون
by feelings of solidarity, loyalty, pride, patriotism,
بمشاعر التضامن والولاء والفخر والوطنية،
towards their country or towards their ethnic group.
تجاه بلادهم أو تجاه جماعتهم العرقية.
Regardless of your politics, many people feel proud to be American,
بغض النظر عن سياستك، كثير من الناس فخورون لكونهم أمريكيون
and they favor Americans over other countries.
ويفضلون الأمريكيين على البلاد الأخرى.
Residents of other countries feel the same about their nation,
والمواطنون في البلاد الأخرى لديهم نفس الشعور تجاه بلادهم،
and we feel the same about our ethnicities.
ولدينا نفس الشعور نحو أعراقنا.
Now some of you may reject this.
الآن قد يرفض بعضكم هذا.
Some of you may be so cosmopolitan
بعض منكم قد يكون عالميا
that you think that ethnicity and nationality
بحيث تعتقدون أن العرقية والوطنية
should hold no moral sway.
يجب أن لا تحمل تأثيرا أخلاقيا.
But even you sophisticates accept
لكن حتى المحنكون قبلوا
that there should be some pull
أنه يجب أن يكون هناك بعض الجذب
towards the in-group in the domain of friends and family,
تجاه داخل المجموعة في نطاق الأصدقاء والعائلة،
of people you're close to,
من الناس المقربين لكم،
and so even you make a distinction
مع ذلك حتى أنت تميز
between us versus them.
بين نحن ضدهم
Now, this distinction is natural enough
الآن، التمييز طبيعي بصورة كافية
and often moral enough, but it can go awry,
وغالبًا أخلاقي بصورة كافية، لكنه يمكن أن ينحرف،
and this was part of the research
وهذا كان جزء من البحث
of the great social psychologist Henri Tajfel.
لأعظم عالم نفس واجتماع هنري تاجيفل.
Tajfel was born in Poland in 1919.
ولد تاجيفل في بولندا عام 1919.
He left to go to university in France,
غادر إلى فرنسا ليلتحق بالجامعة،
because as a Jew, he couldn't go to university in Poland,
لأنه كيهودي، لا يمكنه الالتحاق بالجامعة في بولندا
and then he enlisted in the French military
ثم تطوع في الجيش الفرنسي
in World War II.
في الحرب العالمية الثانية.
He was captured and ended up
تم القبض عليه وانتهى به المطاف
in a prisoner of war camp,
في سجن لأسرى الحرب،
and it was a terrifying time for him,
وكان هذا وقتا مرعبا بالنسبة له،
because if it was discovered that he was a Jew,
لأنه إن أُكتشف أنه يهودي،
he could have been moved to a concentration camp,
كان سيتم نقله لمعسكر اعتقال،
where he most likely would not have survived.
حيث لا أمل في النجاة في الأغلب
And in fact, when the war ended and he was released,
وفي واقع الأمر، بعد الانتهاء من الحرب تم الإفراج عنه،
most of his friends and family were dead.
معظم أصدقائه وعائلته قد ماتوا.
He got involved in different pursuits.
انخرط في نشاطات مختلفة.
He helped out the war orphans.
ساعد أيتام الحرب.
But he had a long-lasting interest
لكن كان لديه اهتمام طويل الأمد
in the science of prejudice,
بعلم التعصب،
and so when a prestigious British scholarship
وحين فتحت منحة دراسية بريطانية مرموقة على الصور النمطية
on stereotypes opened up, he applied for it,
قدم طلبًا للحصول عليها،
and he won it,
وفاز بها،
and then he began this amazing career.
ومن ثم بدأ تلك المهنة المذهلة.
And what started his career is an insight
وما بدأ حياته المهنية بصيرة
that the way most people were thinking
أن الطريقة التي كان معظم الناس يفكر بها
about the Holocaust was wrong.
في الهولوكوست خاطئة.
Many people, most people at the time,
كثير من الناس، معظم الناس في ذلك الوقت،
viewed the Holocaust as sort of representing
يرون الهولوكوست كنوع يمثل
some tragic flaw on the part of the Germans,
خللا مأساويا في الجانب الألماني،
some genetic taint, some authoritarian personality.
بعض العيوب الوراثية، وبعض الشخصية السلطوية.
And Tajfel rejected this.
ورفض تاجيفل ذلك.
Tajfel said what we see in the Holocaust
قال تاجيفل بأن ما نراه في الهولوكوست
is just an exaggeration
مجرد تهويل
of normal psychological processes
لعمليات نفسية طبيعية
that exist in every one of us.
توجد في كل فرد منا
And to explore this, he did a series of classic studies
ولتوضيح هذا، أجرى سلسلة من الدراسات التقليدية
with British adolescents.
على فتيان بريطانيين.
And in one of his studies, what he did was he asked
وفي إحدى دراساته ما فعله هو سؤال
the British adolescents all sorts of questions,
الفتيان البريطانيين كل أنواع الأسئلة،
and then based on their answers, he said,
وثم بناءً على إجابتهم، قال،
"I've looked at your answers, and based on the answers,
"قد بحثت إجابتكم، وبناءً عليها،
I have determined that you are either" —
قد قررت أنكم سواء" -
he told half of them —
أخبر نصفهم -
"a Kandinsky lover, you love the work of Kandinsky,
"محبي كاندينسكي، محبي عمل كاندينسكي،
or a Klee lover, you love the work of Klee."
أو محبي كلي، محبي عمل كلي."
It was entirely bogus.
كانت وهمية تمامًا.
Their answers had nothing to do with Kandinsky or Klee.
إجاباتهم ليس لها علاقة بهما.
He just arbitrarily divided them up.
قد قام فقط بتقسيمهم بطريقة تعسفية
But what he found was, these categories mattered,
لكن ما وجده هو، أن هذه الفئات ممهمة،
so when he later gave the subjects money,
لذلك لاحقًا حين أعطى الفتيان مالا،
they would prefer to give the money
فضلوا إعطاء المال
to members of their own group
لأعضاء مجموعتهم
than members of the other group.
على إعطائه لأعضاء المجموعة الأخرى.
Worse, they were actually most interested
الأسوأ من ذلك، كانوا حقًا أكثر أهتمامًا
in establishing a difference
بترسيخ الاختلاف
between their group and other groups,
بين مجموعتهم والمجموعات الأخرى،
so they would give up money for their own group
لذلك تخلوا عن المال لصالح مجموعتهم
if by doing so they could give the other group even less.
إذا كان بفعل ذلك يمكن إعطاء المجموعة الأخرى أقل.
This bias seems to show up very early.
يبدوا هذا التحيز ليظهر في وقت مبكر جدًا
So my colleague and wife, Karen Wynn, at Yale
لذلك رفيقي وزوجته، كارين وين، في جامعة ييل
has done a series of studies with babies
أجروا سلسلة دراسات على الأطفال
where she exposes babies to puppets,
حيث تعرض الأطفال على العرائس،
and the puppets have certain food preferences.
والعرائس لديها تفضيلات غذاء معينة.
So one of the puppets might like green beans.
حيث أحد العرائس قد يحب الفاصوليا الخضراء.
The other puppet might like graham crackers.
أخرى قد ترغب في رقائق جراهام.
They test the babies own food preferences,
إنهم يختبرون أذواق الأطفال الغذائية،
and babies typically prefer the graham crackers.
والأطفال يفضلون رقائق جراهام عادةً
But the question is, does this matter to babies
لكن السؤال هو، هل يهم الأطفال
in how they treat the puppets? And it matters a lot.
كيفية التعامل مع الدمى؟ وكان يهم كثيرًا.
They tend to prefer the puppet
كانوا يميلون لتفضيل العروسة
who has the same food tastes that they have,
التي لها نفس مذاق الطعام الذي لديهم،
and worse, they actually prefer puppets
والأسوأ من ذلك، كانوا حقًا يفضلون العرائس
who punish the puppet with the different food taste.
التي تعاقب العروسة ذات المذاق المختلف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We see this sort of in-group, out-group psychology all the time.
نرى علم نفس هذا من نوع "داخل المجموعة" و"خارج المجموعة" طوال الوقت.
We see it in political clashes
نراه في النزاعات السياسية
within groups with different ideologies.
بين مجموعات ذات أيديولوجيات مختلفة.
We see it in its extreme in cases of war,
نراها في أقصى حدودها في حالات الحرب.
where the out-group isn't merely given less,
حيث خارج المجموعة لا يعطون أقل فقط،
but dehumanized,
بل يفقدون إنسانيتهم،
as in the Nazi perspective of Jews
كمنظور النازيين لليهود
as vermin or lice,
كقمل وهوام.
or the American perspective of Japanese as rats.
أو منظور الأمريكان لليابانيين كجرذان.
Stereotypes can also go awry.
يمكن أيضًا للصور النمطية أن تنحرف.
So often they're rational and useful,
لذلك في الغالب تكون عقلانية ومفيدة
but sometimes they're irrational,
لكن في بعض الأحيان غير عقلانية
they give the wrong answers,
إنهم يجيبون خطأ
and other times
والأوقات الأخرى
they lead to plainly immoral consequences.
يقودون بوضوح إلى عواقب غير أخلاقية.
And the case that's been most studied
والحالة التي تم دراستها كثيرًا
is the case of race.
هي حالة السلالة.
There was a fascinating study
كانت هناك دراسة رائعة
prior to the 2008 election
قبل انتخابات 2008
where social psychologists looked at the extent
حيث نظر علماء النفس والاجتماع للحد
to which the candidates were associated with America,
الذي يصل له ارتباط المرشحين بأمريكا،
as in an unconscious association with the American flag.
كالارتباط اللاواعي بالعلم الأمريكي.
And in one of their studies they compared
وفي إحدى دراساتهم قارنوا
Obama and McCain, and they found McCain
أوباما وماكين، ووجدوا بأن ماكين
is thought of as more American than Obama,
يُعتقد أنه أمريكي أكثر من أوباما،
and to some extent, people aren't that surprised by hearing that.
ولحد ما، لم يتفاجأ الناس لسماع ذلك.
McCain is a celebrated war hero,
يعد ماكين بطل حرب مشهور
and many people would explicitly say
وكثير من الناس يقولون صراحةً
he has more of an American story than Obama.
أن لديه قصة أمريكية أكثر من أوباما.
But they also compared Obama
لكنهم قارنوا بين أوباما أيضًا
to British Prime Minister Tony Blair,
ورئيس وزراء بريطانيا توني بلير،
and they found that Blair was also thought of
ووجدوا أيضًا أن بلير يُعتقد أنه
as more American than Obama,
أمريكي أكثر من أوباما،
even though subjects explicitly understood
حتى رغم فهم المُجرى عليهم الدراسة صراحةً
that he's not American at all.
أنه ليس أمريكي.
But they were responding, of course,
لكنهم أجابوا، بالطبع،
to the color of his skin.
لصالح لون بشرته.
These stereotypes and biases
هذه الصور النمطية والتحيزات
have real-world consequences,
لها عواقب في العالم الحقيقي،
both subtle and very important.
كلاهما هام.
In one recent study, researchers
في دراسة حديثة، وضع الباحثون
put ads on eBay for the sale of baseball cards.
إعلانات على إي باي لبيع كروت بيسبول.
Some of them were held by white hands,
بعض منها تحمله أيادي بيضاء،
others by black hands.
والبعض الآخر أيادي سوداء.
They were the same baseball cards.
كانت نفس كروت البيسبول.
The ones held by black hands
الكروت التي في أيادي سوداء
got substantially smaller bids
حصلت على عطاءات أصغر بصورة ملحوظة
than the ones held by white hands.
من التي في أيادي بيضاء.
In research done at Stanford,
في بحث تم في ستانفورد
psychologists explored the case of people
أوضح علماء النفس حالة الناس
sentenced for the murder of a white person.
المدانين بقتل شخص أبيض.
It turns out, holding everything else constant,
اتضح، وكل الملابسات واحدة،
you are considerably more likely to be executed
أنكم عرضه بصورة كبيرة للإعدام
if you look like the man on the right
لو كنتم مثل الشخص الذي على اليمين
than the man on the left,
أكثر من الشخص الذي على اليسار،
and this is in large part because
وهذا بصورة كبيرة لأن
the man on the right looks more prototypically black,
الرجل على اليمين تبدوا أصوله من السود،
more prototypically African-American,
أكثر من الأصول الأفروأمريكية،
and this apparently influences people's decisions
ويؤثر هذا تقريبا على قرارات الناس
over what to do about him.
أكثر مما يجب القيام به لهم.
So now that we know about this,
لذلك الآن هذا ما نعرف عن ذلك،
how do we combat it?
كيف يمكننا مكافحته؟
And there are different avenues.
وهناك وسائل مختلفة.
One avenue is to appeal
أحد الوسائل هي مناشدة
to people's emotional responses,
استجابات الناس العاطفية،
to appeal to people's empathy,
مناشدة رحمة الناس،
and we often do that through stories.
وفي الغالب نقوم بذلك عبر قصص.
So if you are a liberal parent
لذلك إذا كنت والدا ليبراليا
and you want to encourage your children
وأردت أن تحفز أبناءك
to believe in the merits of nontraditional families,
على الاعتقاد في مزايا العائلات الغير تقليدية،
you might give them a book like this. ["Heather Has Two Mommies"]
ربما عليك إعطائهم كتاب مثل هذا "هيثر له والدتان"
If you are conservative and have a different attitude,
إن كنت من المحافظين ولك موقف مختلف،
you might give them a book like this.
ربما عليك إعطائهم كتاب مثل هذا.
(Laughter) ["Help! Mom! There Are Liberals under My Bed!"]
"النجدة! أمي! ليبراليون تحت سريري!"
But in general, stories can turn
لكن في العموم، القصص يمكن أن تحول
anonymous strangers into people who matter,
الغرباء المجهولين لأناس لهم أهمية،
and the idea that we care about people
والفكرة هي أننا نعتني بأمر الناس
when we focus on them as individuals
حين نركز عليهم كأفراد
is an idea which has shown up across history.
هي الفكرة التي ظهرت عبر التاريخ.
So Stalin apocryphally said,
لذلك قال ستانلي،
"A single death is a tragedy,
"موت فرد مأساة،
a million deaths is a statistic,"
موت مليون إحصائية،"
and Mother Teresa said,
وقالت الأم تريزا،
"If I look at the mass, I will never act.
"إذا نظرت لحشد، لن أتحرك أبدًا.
If I look at the one, I will."
إذا نظرت لواحد، سوف أتحرك."
Psychologists have explored this.
أوضح علماء النفس هذا.
For instance, in one study,
على سبيل المثال، في دراسة،
people were given a list of facts about a crisis,
الناس الذين تم إعطائهم قائمة من الحقائق عن الأزمة،
and it was seen how much they would donate
لنرى بكم سوف يتبرعون
to solve this crisis,
لحل تلك الأزمة،
and another group was given no facts at all
ومجموعة أخرى لم يتم إعطائهم أي حقائق
but they were told of an individual
ولكن تم إخبارهم عن فرد
and given a name and given a face,
واسمه ووجهه،
and it turns out that they gave far more.
واتضح أنهم منحوا أكثر بكثير.
None of this I think is a secret
ولا شيء من هذا أعتقد أنه سر
to the people who are engaged in charity work.
للناس المنخرطين في عمل خيري.
People don't tend to deluge people
الناس لا يمليون إلى غمر الناس
with facts and statistics.
بالحقائق والإحصائيات.
Rather, you show them faces,
لكن، أروهم وجههم،
you show them people.
أروهم ناس.
It's possible that by extending our sympathies
فمن الممكن توسيع شفقتنا
to an individual, they can spread
على فرد، يمكن أن تنتشر
to the group that the individual belongs to.
للمجموعة التي ينتمي إليها هذا الفرد.
This is Harriet Beecher Stowe.
هذه هاريت بيتشر ستو.
The story, perhaps apocryphal,
القصة، ربما تكون ملفقة،
is that President Lincoln invited her
هي أن الرئيس لينكولن دعاها
to the White House in the middle of the Civil War
للبيت الأبيض في منتصف الحرب الأهلية
and said to her,
وقال لها
"So you're the little lady who started this great war."
"إذًا أنت السيدة الصغيرة التي بدأت هذه الحرب الضخمة."
And he was talking about "Uncle Tom's Cabin."
وكان يتحدث عن "كوخ العم توم."
"Uncle Tom's Cabin" is not a great book of philosophy
ليس "كوخ العم توم" كتابا قيما في الفلسفة
or of theology or perhaps not even literature,
أو علم اللاهوت أو ربما ولا حتى الأدب،
but it does a great job
لكنه عمل قيم
of getting people to put themselves in the shoes
لجعل الناس يضعون أنفسهم في أحذية
of people they wouldn't otherwise be in the shoes of,
أناس لم يودوا من ناحية أخري أن يكونوا في أحذيتهم
put themselves in the shoes of slaves.
وضعوا أنفسهم في أحذية العبيد.
And that could well have been a catalyst
ويمكن أن يكون ذلك حافزا جيدا
for great social change.
لتغيير اجتماعي كبير.
More recently, looking at America
حديثًا أكثر، بالنظر لأمريكا
in the last several decades,
في العقود الأخيرة،
there's some reason to believe that shows like "The Cosby Show"
هناك سبب ما للاعتقاد أن عروض مثل "كوسبي شو"
radically changed American attitudes towards African-Americans,
غيرت المواقف الأمريكية جذريًا تجاه الأفروأمريكيين
while shows like "Will and Grace" and "Modern Family"
في حين عروض مثل "ويل أند غريس" و"مودرن فاميلي"
changed American attitudes
غيرت المواقف الأمريكية
towards gay men and women.
تجاه الرجال والنساء الشواذ.
I don't think it's an exaggeration to say
لا أعتقد أنه من التهويل أن أقول
that the major catalyst in America for moral change
أن الحافز الأكبر في أمريكا للتغيير الأخلاقي
has been a situation comedy.
كان كوميديا الموقف.
But it's not all emotions,
لكنها ليست كل المشاعر،
and I want to end by appealing
وأريد أن أنهي بمناشدة
to the power of reason.
لقوة المنطق.
At some point in his wonderful book
في نقطة ما في كتابه الرائع
"The Better Angels of Our Nature,"
"أفضل ملائكة طبيعتنا"
Steven Pinker says,
يقول ستيفين بينكر،
the Old Testament says love thy neighbor,
يقول العهد القديم أحب جارك،
and the New Testament says love thy enemy,
ويقول العهد الحديث أحب عدوك،
but I don't love either one of them, not really,
لكني لا أحب أحدا منهما، ليس حقيقة،
but I don't want to kill them.
لكنني لا أريد أن أقتلهما.
I know I have obligations to them,
أعلم أنه لدي واجبات تجاههما،
but my moral feelings to them, my moral beliefs
لكن مشاعري الأخلاقية لهما، ومعتقداتي الأخلاقية
about how I should behave towards them,
عن كيف يجب التصرف نحوهما،
aren't grounded in love.
لا ترتكز على الحب.
What they're grounded in is the understanding of human rights,
ما ترتكز عليه هو فهم حقوق الإنسان،
a belief that their life is as valuable to them
الإيمان بحياتهم كقيمة لهم
as my life is to me,
كما حياتي بالنسبة لي،
and to support this, he tells a story
وليدعم ذلك، يحكي قصة
by the great philosopher Adam Smith,
الفليسوف الكبير آدم سميث،
and I want to tell this story too,
وأريد أن أحكي تلك القصة أيضًا،
though I'm going to modify it a little bit
رغم أني بصدد تعديلها قليلًا
for modern times.
للعصور الحديثة.
So Adam Smith starts by asking you to imagine
حسنًا، بدأ آدم سميث يطلب منكم تخيل
the death of thousands of people,
موت الآلاف من الناس،
and imagine that the thousands of people
وتخيل أن الآلاف من الناس
are in a country you are not familiar with.
ليسوا من البلد المألوفة لك.
It could be China or India or a country in Africa.
يمكن أن تكون الصين أو الهند أو دولة من أفريقيا.
And Smith says, how would you respond?
وقال سميث، كيف استجابتك؟
And you would say, well that's too bad,
وأنت ستقول، حسنًا هذا سيء جدًا،
and you'd go on to the rest of your life.
وسوف تستمر في حياتك.
If you were to open up The New York Times online or something,
لو كنت تفتح النيويورك تايمز على الإنترنيت
and discover this, and in fact this happens to us all the time,
وتكتشف هذا، وفي واقع الأمر يحدث هذا لنا طيلة الوقت،
we go about our lives.
نحن نسير في حياتنا.
But imagine instead, Smith says,
لكن تخيل بدلًا عن ذلك، يقول سميث،
you were to learn that tomorrow
كنت لتعلم أن غدا
you were to have your little finger chopped off.
قد يقطع أصبعك الصغير.
Smith says, that would matter a lot.
يقول سميث، ذلك سوف يهم كثيرًا.
You would not sleep that night
لن تنام هذه الليلة
wondering about that.
قلقا حيال ذلك.
So this raises the question:
لذلك هذا يثير تساؤلًا:
Would you sacrifice thousands of lives
هل ستضحي بآلاف من الأرواح
to save your little finger?
لتنجي أصبعك الصغير؟
Now answer this in the privacy of your own head,
الآن أجب في قرارة نفسك،
but Smith says, absolutely not,
لكن سميث يقول، لا مطلقًا
what a horrid thought.
ما هذا الفكر البشع.
And so this raises the question,
ولذلك هذا يثير تساؤلًا،
and so, as Smith puts it,
ولذلك، كما يضعه سميث،
"When our passive feelings are almost always
"حين تكون مشاعرنا السلبية في الأغلب دائمًا
so sordid and so selfish,
دنيئة جدًا وأنانية جدًا،
how comes it that our active principles
كيف لمبادئنا الإيجابية
should often be so generous and so noble?"
أن تكون غالبًا كريمة جدًا ونبيلة جدًا؟"
And Smith's answer is, "It is reason,
وإجابة سميث هي، "إنه المنطق
principle, conscience.
والمبدأ والضمير.
[This] calls to us,
[هذا] يدعونا،
with a voice capable of astonishing the most presumptuous of our passions,
بصوت قادر على إذهال أكثرعواطفنا تجرؤًا،
that we are but one of the multitude,
ذلك لأننا واحد من عديد،
in no respect better than any other in it."
لسنا بأفضل من الغير داخله بأي مقياس."
And this last part is what is often described
وهذا الجزء الأخير هو غالبًا ما يوصف
as the principle of impartiality.
كمبدأ التجرد.
And this principle of impartiality manifests itself
ويبرهن مبدأ التجرد هذا عن نفسه
in all of the world's religions,
في كل عقائد العالم
in all of the different versions of the golden rule,
في جميع الإصدارات المختلفة للقاعدة الذهبية،
and in all of the world's moral philosophies,
وفي كل فلسفات العالم الأخلاقية،
which differ in many ways
والتي تختلف في نواح عديدة
but share the presupposition that we should judge morality
لكن تشترك في المسلمات
from sort of an impartial point of view.
من وجهة النظر المتجردة نوعا ما.
The best articulation of this view
أفضل تعبير عن هذا الرأي
is actually, for me, it's not from a theologian or from a philosopher,
في الواقع، بالنسبة لي، ليس من لاهوتي أو من فليسوف،
but from Humphrey Bogart
لكن من هامفري بوجارت
at the end of "Casablanca."
في نهاية "كازابلانكا"
So, spoiler alert, he's telling his lover
لذلك، تنبيه مفسد، يخبر حبيبته
that they have to separate
أنه يجب أن ينفصلوا
for the more general good,
من أجل خير أعم
and he says to her, and I won't do the accent,
ويقول لها، ولن أقوم بأداء اللكنة،
but he says to her, "It doesn't take much to see
لكنه يقول لها، "لن يمر وقت كثير قبل أن تري
that the problems of three little people
أن مشاكل ثلاثة أناس صغيرين
don't amount to a hill of beans in this crazy world."
لا تصل لتل من الفول في هذا العالم المجنون.
Our reason could cause us to override our passions.
منطقنا يمكن أن يسبب لنا تجاوز عواطفنا.
Our reason could motivate us
منطقنا يمكن أن يحفزنا
to extend our empathy,
لنحد من تعاطفنا،
could motivate us to write a book like "Uncle Tom's Cabin,"
يمكن أن يحفزنا لنكتب كتاب مثل "كوخ العم توم."
or read a book like "Uncle Tom's Cabin,"
أو قراءة كتاب مثل "كوخ العم توم،"
and our reason can motivate us to create
ومنطقنا يستطيع أن يحفزنا لخلق
customs and taboos and laws
تقاليد ومحرمات وقوانين
that will constrain us
التي من شأنها أن تقيدنا
from acting upon our impulses
من التصرف باندفاع
when, as rational beings, we feel
عندما، ككائنات عاقلة، نشعر
we should be constrained.
أننا يجب أن نُقيد.
This is what a constitution is.
هذا هو االدستور.
A constitution is something which was set up in the past
الدستور هو شيء قد أُعد في الماضي
that applies now in the present,
ويطبق الآن في الحاضر،
and what it says is,
وما يقوله هو،
no matter how much we might to reelect
لا يهم إلى أي مدى يمكننا إعادة إنتخاب
a popular president for a third term,
رئيس ذي شعبية لفترة رئاسية ثالثة،
no matter how much white Americans might choose
لا يهم إلى أي مدى يمكن للأمريكيين البيض
to feel that they want to reinstate the institution of slavery, we can't.
اختيار أن يشعروا أنهم يريدون إعادة مؤسسة الرق، لا يمكننا ذلك.
We have bound ourselves.
قيّدنا أنفسنا.
And we bind ourselves in other ways as well.
ونقيد أنفسنا بطرق أخرى أيضًا.
We know that when it comes to choosing somebody
نعرف ذلك حين تأتي لاختيار شخص ما
for a job, for an award,
لوظيفة، أو لجائزة،
we are strongly biased by their race,
نتحيز بشدة لسلالتهم،
we are biased by their gender,
نتحيز لجنسهم،
we are biased by how attractive they are,
نتحيز لمدى جاذبيتهم،
and sometimes we might say, "Well fine, that's the way it should be."
وأحيانًا يمكن القول، "حسنًا جيد، هذا هو المفروض"
But other times we say, "This is wrong."
لكن في أوقات أخرى نقول، "هذا خطأ."
And so to combat this,
ولذلك لمكافحة هذا،
we don't just try harder,
ليس مجرد أن نحاول بجد أكثر،
but rather what we do is we set up situations
لكن بل ما نقوم به هو إعداد حالات
where these other sources of information can't bias us,
حيث هذه المصادر الأخرى للمعلومات لا تستطيع أن تجعلنا منحازين،
which is why many orchestras
وهذا سبب أن العديد من فرق
audition musicians behind screens,
الأوركسترا تختبر الموسيقيين خلف شاشات،
so the only information they have
لذلك المعلومات الوحيدة
is the information they believe should matter.
التي يحصلون عليها هي المعلومات التي يعتقدون أنها تهم.
I think prejudice and bias
أعتقد أن التعصب والتحيز
illustrate a fundamental duality of human nature.
يوضح الازدواجية الجوهرية في الطبيعة البشرية
We have gut feelings, instincts, emotions,
لدينا مشاعر جريئة وغرائز وعواطف،
and they affect our judgments and our actions
وهذه تؤثر على أحكامنا وأفعالنا
for good and for evil,
للخير والشر،
but we are also capable of rational deliberation
لكننا قادرون أيضًا على المداولة العقلانية
and intelligent planning,
والتخطيط الذكي،
and we can use these to, in some cases,
ونستطيع استخدامها، في بعض الحالات،
accelerate and nourish our emotions,
لتسريع وتغذية عواطفنا،
and in other cases staunch them.
وفي حالات أخرى نكبحها.
And it's in this way
وبهذه الطريقة
that reason helps us create a better world.
يساعدنا المنطق على خلق عالم أفضل.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)